A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Projects FA733
Rockefeller Archive Center
- D-495: Grants-In-Aid to talented Artists (Ford Foundation initiated), 1958-1962 (Reel P-1030)
  See also: Ford Foundation records, Projects, D-499: Solo artists program to commission and arrange performances of new works.
  Six programs are included in this appropriation:
  (1) 3-year purchase program for painters and sculptors (Ford Foundation grant 06290107, PA62-107)
  (2) Program to provide talented young singers with opportunities to perform leading roles with civic opera companies
  (3) 3-year program of administrative internships in professional and community opera, symphony and theater groups
  (4) Collaboration of painters and sculptors in production designs of local theater and opera groups (D-497)
  (5) Opportunities for professional, community and academic choral directors (D-498)
  (6) Solo artists program to commission and arrange performances of new works (D-499).
- D-497: Collaboration of painters and sculptors in production designs of local theater and opera groups (Ford Foundation initiated), 1961 (Reel P-1030)
  See also project file D-495, "Grants-In-Aid to talented Artists".
- D-498: Opportunities for professional, community and academic choral directors (Ford Foundation initiated), 1961 (Reel P-1030)
- D-499: Solo artists program to commission and arrange performances of new works (Ford Foundation initiated), 1961 (Reel P-1030)
- D-500: Hartwick College - general program, 1961-1962 (Reel P-1030)
- D-502: Washington University, St. Louis - Summer institute on urban life, 1961 (Reel P-1030)
- D-503: Learning Resources Institute - college credit courses on all [television] networks, 1961 (Reel P-1030)
- D-506: Cornell University - Center for training and research in school psychology, 1961 (Reel P-1030)
- D-508: University of Utah - Institute for the study of mathematics by business school faculty, 1961 (Reel P-1030)
- D-509: Northwest Nazarene College - general support, 1961-1963 (Reel P-1030)
- D-513: American Operatic Repertoire (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1030)
  Request: $950,000 over 8 year period. Support to complete the Foundation's demonstration of the contemporary American operatic repertoire.
- D-514: Washington Housing Association (Washington, D.C.) - establishing a citizens planning and housing association in the Washington metropolitan area., 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-516: Michigan State University - experimental college at Michigan State University, 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-517: University of Puget Sound - general support (Reel P-1031)
- D-518: College of the Holy Cross - General program (Reel P-1031)
- D-519: University of Oregon - Identification and evaluation of motivational changes produced by education and training, 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-520: Western Reserve University - Mathematics "bridge-up" for economics and business professors, 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-521: University of Michigan - procedures for automated instruction via audio-aural aspects of music theory, 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-530: Associated Rocky Mountain Universities - Study of arid lands problems, 1961-1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-531: International Commission of Jurists - International Congress of Jurists (August 1962), 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-532: University of Oklahoma - enriched Master's program, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-533: Committee on Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students - general support, 1963 (Reel P-1031)
- D-536: Hebrew University (Jerusalem, Israel) - program of African studies, 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-538: Illinois Supreme Court Committee on Jury Instructions in Criminal Cases - reporter system of operation, 1961-1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-540: Kentucky Committee for Correctional Research - Study of Kentucky's adult prison system, 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-542: Business History Foundation, Inc. - History of American business, 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-543: National Academy of Sciences - Support world conference on the international geophysical year and the (1963) thirteenth general assembly of the Internatioal Union of Geodesy and Geophysics, 1961-1963 (Reel P-1031)
- D-551: Marietta College - general support, 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-552: University of Wyoming - Support study in adult education, 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-553: Strengthening of Residential Theater in the United States (Ford Foundation initiated), 1961-1962 (Reel P-1031)
  Four part program to strengthen residential theater in the United States:
  (1) Playwright's theater in New York - establishment by stages of a theater largely devoted to the new American play
  (2) Consolidation of the positions of leading residential theaters
  (3) Improvement in the training of classical actors for the residential theater
  (4) Other new developments in residential theater.
- D-557: World University Service - Education international understanding in American colleges, 1961-1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-561: Western States Small School Project (WSSSP) (Ford Foundation initiated), 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-563: Western Reserve University - Relationship between social values and social behavior in middle class youth, 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-567: American Judicature Society - legal profession and judicial selection, 1961-1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-571: In-Service Training in Agriculture, Burma (Ford Foundation initiated), 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-590: International Research Institute - Social science research studies in international affairs, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-605: Michigan State University, Oakland - New program in business-economics education, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-608: Pan American Union - Inter-American seminar on science journalism, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-611: University of Washington, Seattle - Support for visiting lecturer lecture series, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-615: Washington University, St. Louis - Program to strengthen engineering education in the midwest, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-623: Tulane University - Forgivable predoctoral loans to future engineering teachers, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-625: University of Pittsburgh - Study of political elites in Eastern Europe, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-627: Heidelberg College - general support, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-634: Housing for Visiting Scholars and Researchers in Africa (Ford Foundation initiated), 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-636: New York School of Social Work, Columbia University - Conference on community treatment under conditions of maximum control, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-640: Ministry of Commerce and Industry, Government of India - International study team on small industry perspective planning and financing, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1031)
- D-641: University of Missouri - Summer institute for teachers of economics in junior colleges, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-642: Clemon College - Engineering faculty growth and improvement program, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-644: Festival Foundation, Inc. - Support for festival of two worlds student program, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-645: Montana Department of Public Instruction - Introduce and use instruction by television in Montana schools, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-646: University of California, Berkeley - Administration of justice to juveniles, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-649: American Academy of Arts and Sciences - Series of radio programs based on the publication Daedalus, in cooperation of the Educational Radio Network (WGBH)., 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-650: Migrant Children's Fund, Inc. - Educational program for migrant children, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-651: Montana District Court, First Judicial District - internship program, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-652: United States National Student Association - Support for first student national affairs program, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1031)
- D-655: Shaw University - Program on African studies, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-656: Committee for Economic Development - Publication of research papers, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-657: Johns Hopkins University - Research on economics of health, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-660: International Association of Plastic Arts; Institute of International Education - Congress of the International Association of Plastic Arts, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-662: University of Pennsylvania - College honors program in the humanities and sciences for the gifted student, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-663: Educational building consultant for National Institute of Education, India (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-664: Ohio Academy of Science - Support for program development, 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-667: Projects for Improving the Utilization of Manpower Resources (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1031)
- D-670: Engineering faculty development through aid to graduate students (Ford Foundation initiated), 1961 (Reel P-1031)
- D-671: Evaluation of program for stimulating faculty/student research in public affairs (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-672: University of Maine - New England-Atlantic provinces study center, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-673: Wake Forest College - Strengthening of preparation for college teaching, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1032)
- D-675: Cornell University - Experimental program for the preparation of school counselors, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1032)
- D-678: International Planned Parenthood Federation - Program to expedite world fertility control, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-680: Texas Christian University - Support 3-year master's program, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1032)
- D-681: Randolph-Macon Woman's College - To prepare students of liberal arts colleges for teaching in secondary schools, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-682: University of Toledo - Program in engineering science, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-683: University of Wichita - Combined research-experimental program of instruction in the training of administrators, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-684: Relocation Projects and Management Seminars in Public Housing (Ford Foundation initiated), 1961 (Reel P-1032)
  (1) Demonstration projects to improve resettlement of older persons displaced by urban renewal
  (2) Training seminars to improve management of public housing for the elderly.
- D-685: University of Michigan - Analysis of American colleges and universities, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-686: Dartmouth College - New England urban studies program, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-690: Children's Aid Society - Teenage employment problems, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-691: Training of Economists from Overseas and for Overseas Services (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962-1963 (Reel P-1032)
- D-694: Institute of International Education - Fellowship assistance to the Bayreuth Festival Master Classes, Inc., 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-695: Southern Illinois University - Expirement in urban community development and social research in East St. Louis, Illinois, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-700: Catholic University of America - Research "The Changing Surface of Contemporary China", 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-706: National Education Association - Study of shortage of teachers in universities, colleges, and junior colleges, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-709: European Cultural Centre - general support, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
  Includes correspondence between Denis de Rougemont and Shepard Stone. Project description: "Fund to organize guest lectures and seminars, prepare general reference library, publish bibliographical material, promote establishment of centers in various cultural regions and subsequent establishment of a federation of regional Cultural Centres." Request $50,000 per year, 5 years.
- D-710: Mont Holyoke College - graduate program in African studies, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1032)
- D-711: University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) - pilot study on interdisciplinary top management decision research, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-712: Adelphi College - general support, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-713: Kentucky Authority for Educational Television - establishing an educational television network, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-714: American Friends Service Committee - Algerian community development and training program, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-715: Lawrence College, Wisconsin - program in international studies, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-717: Center for International Economic Growth - Population growth in relation to economic and social development, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-718: George Washington University - Program of Graduate School of Public Law, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-719: Greater New York Council for Foreign Students, Inc. - English in action project, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-721: Fellowship Program in Business Administration and Economics, 1963-1964 (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-722: Utah Department of Public Instruction - Western states cooperative dropout project, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-732: Institute of International Education - Research in reproduction physiology and fertility control, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1032)
- D-733: Dartmouth College, Amos Tuck School of Business Administration - program of studies in the administration of hospital and health resources, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-737: University of Kentucky - graduate work in economics and business, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-739: United Nations Education Centre, University of British Columbia - support for program, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1032)
- D-742: University of Alabama - Influence of reapportionment on state legislative policies, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-743: University of Michigan - Graduate Program in Comparative History, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-746: Association Scientifique Européenne pour La Prevision Economique a Moyen et a Long Terme (ASEPELT) - preparation of book on European trade, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1032)
- D-748: University of Santo Domingo (Dominican Republic) - establishment of an institute of economic research, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-749: Greater Washington Educational Television, Inc. - partial support for purchase of mobile unit, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-750: Tufts University; Lincoln Filene Center for Citizenship and Public Affairs - Nationwhide program in the teaching of ideologies and world affairs at the secondary level, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-755: University College, Ibadan - Survey of extra-mural education in Nigeria, 1962 (Reel P-1032)
- D-759: Research and Training in Reproductive Physiology in the United States and Europe (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962-1963 (Reel P-1033)
  Project description:
  "(1) Conferences: Albert Taylor plans to bring together a group of immunologists to discuss the potential of immunology as a path to optimum fertility control. Dr. Hudson Hoagland, would bring a group of students together to discuss reproductive research.
  (2) Research stipends for medical students (up to ten schools)
  (3) FF projects to cover compensation and expenses for U.S. and European specialists
  (4) Initial grants to U.S. centers of research and training in reproductive biology
  (5)Initial grants to European centers of research and training in reproductive biology.
  Dr. Aura E. Severinghaus will serve as a program specialist to establish this program."
  Request: $3,250,000.
- D-761: American Association for Middle East Studies - undergraduate Middle East studies in American colleges and universities, 1962 (Reel P-1033)
- D-765: University of Connecticut - Regional summer program in industrial management for engineering students, 1962 (Reel P-1033)
- D-768: Atlanta Public Schools - Interim education program for disadvantaged neighborhoods in Atlanta, 1962 (Reel P-1033)
- D-769: Public Administration Services - Conference on institutional cooperation for the public service, 1962 (Reel P-1033)
- D-776: Encouragement of Economic Growth in the United States (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962-1963 (Reel P-1033)
- D-777: Webb Institute of Naval Architecture - support for graduate program, 1962 (Reel P-1033)
- D-780: Association for Commitment to World Responsibility - establishment of a United Nations University, 1962 (Reel P-1033)
- D-784: Clarkson College of Technology - Study of effectiveness of management simulation as a teaching tool, 1962 (Reel P-1033)
- D-789: Harry S. Truman Library, Institute for National and International Affairs - Grants-in-aid program and foreign research interview program, 1962 (Reel P-1033)
- D-791: Assist professional civic operatic companies to extend their seasons and improve their local financial support (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962-1963 (Reel P-1033)
- D-793: Program to assist the national and regional development of performance and training in ballet (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962-1963 (Reel P-1033)
- D-794: Additional Scholarships in Independent and Professional Schools Training in the Creative Arts (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962-1963 (Reel P-1033, Reel P-1034)
  "(1) One-year 'high-risk' scholarship to entering student after extensive audition
  (2) 'Normal' scholarships to needy students in the second year or beyond who had demonstrated strong professional potential
  (3) A few fellowships to graduating students of the highest artistic achievement".
  Request: $2,000,000.
- D-795: Cornell University - Follow-up study of graduates of the fifth year program in elementary education, 1962 (Reel P-1034)
- D-798: Expirements, Demonstrations and Studies in the Arts (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1034)
  "Appropriation will be used for grants and Foundation-administered projects designed to clarify objectives, set standards, and open avenues in the arts".
  Request: $1,250,000.
- D-800: International Studies in Undergraduate Education (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962-1963 (Reel P-1034)
- D-801: National Institute of Labor Education - Long-term non-residential study institutes for trade union leadership, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1034)
- D-802: Strengthen Approaches to International Cooperation and Peace (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1034)
- D-803: Support of Activities to Strengthen the Atlantic Partnership (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1034)
- D-804: Development of Activities Primarily in Japan, to Strengthen Associations with the United States and Europe (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1034)
- D-805: Modern Language Association of America - Foreign language program, 1962 (Reel P-1034)
- D-806: Wayne State University - Econometric study of the short and long-run incidence of the corporation income taxes, 1962 (Reel P-1034)
- D-807: Northwestern University - United States-Latin American criminal justice exchange program, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1034)
- D-808: Strengthen Teacher Education (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1034)
- D-809: Strengthen Preparation for College Teaching (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1034)
- D-812: Governmental Affairs Institute - Support of an Atlantic Community, 1962 (Reel P-1035)
- D-814: Social Science Research Council - Establishment of Inter-American Social Science Council, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-815: Four Year Program to Strengthen Educational, Scientific, Artistic, and Cultural Institutions in Berlin (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962 (Reel P-1035)
- D-816: George Washington University - Program in employee-management cooperation in the federal government, 1962 (Reel P-1035)
- D-821: Manila Observatory - Heliograph and auxiliary equipment, 1962 (Reel P-1035)
- D-829: Association for the Advancement of Southern Italy - Isernia rural economic development project, 1962 (Reel P-1035)
- D-830: National Association for Attorneys General - Comparative analysis of the powers, duties and operations of the officer of the attorney general, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-837: McGill University - Exchange program between College of Social Welfare, Dacca, and School of Social Work, 1962 (Reel P-1035)
- D-839: Coordinating Secretariat of National Unions of Students - Anti-illiteracy programme in Bolivia and Central America, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-840: Massachusetts Institute of Technology - Study in the area of educational data systems, 1962 (Reel P-1035)
- D-851: University College of Rhodesia and Nyasaland - Establishing an Institute of Statistics, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-852: University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) - opinion leaders program, 1962 (Reel P-1035)
- D-856: International Institute of Administrative Science - Development and training programs for public officials in developing countries, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-862: Brookings Institution - Urban policy conferences, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-867: Duquesne University (Pittsburgh, PA) - Cooperative project to prepare professional personnel to teach in culturally disadvantaged areas, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-869: Morgan State College - Preparation of teachers to work in schools in culturally deprived areas, 1962 (Reel P-1035)
- D-871: Harvard University - Human resource development planning in the Dominican Republic, 1962-1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-874: Public Service Research, Inc. - Study on encouraging secondary school students to intellectual and creative efforts, 1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-875: Wesleyan University - General support, 1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-878: Research on Foreign Area and International Problems (Ford Foundation initiated), 1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-879: State University of New York (SUNY), Long Island Center, Stony Brook, N.Y. - Study of the quantitative approach in elementary school science, 1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-880: World University Service of Canada - Partial support for seminar in Pakistan, 1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-882: New York University - Support for Institute of Hebrew Studies, 1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-885: Board of Education of the City of New York - Summer programs for selected students in elementary, junior high, and senior high schools, 1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-887 Young Men's Christian Association of San Francisco - Develop and demonstrate effective ways for youth to participate more productively and responsibly in American society, 1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-893: Swarthmore College - Summer research program for students of all fields, 1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-898: Board of Education, City of Chicago - Urban youth program, 1963 (Reel P-1035)
- D-899: Fellowships in Economic Development and Business Administration, 1964-1965 (Ford Foundation initiated), 1963 (Reel P-1036)
  See also Ford Foundation grant files for "FELLOWSHIP PROGRAM IN BUSINESS ADMINISTRATION AND ECONOMICS, 1964-65" (grant numbers 06400305 through 06400351, or PA64-305 through PA64-351).
- D-900: National Association of Intergroup Relations Officials - National education service for equal opportunity housing, 1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-901: Program in Health Economics and Administration (Ford Foundation initiated), 1962-1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-903: Community Deliquency Prevention Programs (Ford Foundation initiated), 1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-905: Brown University - Latin American program, 1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-913: International Association of Chiefs of Police, Inc. - Assistance to police in planning control of mass behavior, 1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-921: American Council for Nationalities Service - general program, 1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-925: Northwestern University - Urban affairs study program for newsmen, 1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-927: Rhodes University - Institute of social and economic research, 1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-928: University of Southern California - Search and publication of the Farmington collection motion pictures, 1963 (Reel P-1036)
  Project description: "Funds to search, select, translate, and publish material from its Farmington Plan collection in cinema". Project rejected, June 1963.
- D-930: State University of New York (SUNY), Albany - Suppresion of carbohydrate pathways of endometrium as conception control, 1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-931: United States National Student Association - student project for international responsibility, 1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-933: Royal Canadian Institute - Summer science program for secondary school students, 1963 (Reel P-1036)
- D-934: University of Puerto Rico - Inter-American institute of legal studies, 1963 (Reel P-1036)